Guide to the Lewis Sheldon Welch Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Lewis Sheldon Welch Papers
1870-1934
MS 1084
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
9
(23 boxes)
The papers include correspondence, business records, printed matter, and photographs which document Lewis Sheldon Welch's business, civic, and Yale activities. Nearly half the papers concern Welch's investments in the Saddle Mountain Mining Company of Arizona. The papers also highlight Welch's role as an active Yale alumnus and his interests in New Haven civic affairs, civilian efforts to aid the military during World War I, and repeal of the Prohibition amendment.
Welch, Lewis Sheldon, 1867-1940
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the estate of Lewis S. Welch, 1940.
Arrangement
Arranged in two series: I. Correspondence, 1895-1933. II. Subject Files, 1870-1934.
Scope and Contents
The Lewis Sheldon Welch Papers consist of correspondence, business records, printed matter, and photographs which document Welch's business, civic, and Yale activities. The papers, which date from 1870 to 1934, are most voluminous during the period 1901 to 1921 and nearly half concern Welch's investments in the Saddle Mountain Mining Company of Arizona. Welch's participation in New Haven civic affairs and Yale alumni matters, and his interests in World War I and the repeal of the prohibition amendment are also highlighted in the papers.
Series I contains the majority of material in the papers and all material on Welch's business affairs. Both series include correspondence, clippings, printed matter, and photographs, which are arranged by topic.
Series I includes a small quantity of Welch's incoming general letter files. These alphabetical files date from 1896 to 1898 and 1902 to 1904. Many letters in these files are from Yale classmates and other friends or concern the details of the construction and furnishing of the Welch house. Welch's general outgoing letters for the period 1903-1905 are included in letterpress copybooks in boxes 19 and 20.
These volumes also contain many of Welch's letters relating to the Saddle Mountain Mining Company. The chronologically arranged volumes supplement the large quantity of material on the company, which is arranged by correspondent or type of material, in folders 52-151. The company owned copper mines in Gila County, Arizona, and Welch invested heavily in its operations. He interested classmates, family, and friends in investing, and served on the company's board of directors. In 1906 Welch lost control of the Yale Alumni Weekly and, was almost forced into bankruptcy because of this investment. The files, ca. 1901-1907, contain correspondence with stockholders, officers, and other board members including George B. Chittenden, general manager of the mines; William W. Delano, treasurer; Z. Taylor Emery, president; Stuart Hotchkiss, director; and Story B. Ladd, secretary. Folders entitled "Financial records" and Miscellaneous" contain reports of the general manager, contracts, payrolls, balance sheets, executive committee resolutions, minutes, notices of meetings, lists of stockholders, stock certificates, receipts, furnace reports, and other records which detail company policy, management, and mine operations. Additional reports on conditions at the mines can be found in correpondence with Burnett Goodwin.
Most material under the heading "Yale University" in Series I relates to Welch's activities in behalf of the class of 1889. The files contain correspondence and programs for class reunions, drafts of obituaries for class members, and correspondence concerning financial support for classmates and their families. Only a small quantity of material reflects Welch's service on the Yale Alumni Weekly or the Yale-in-China executive committee.
Welch's civic activities are represented in files on Grace Hospital, the Military Training Corps Association, and the New Haven City Hall. Welch as a director of Grace Hospital participated in discussions of a proposed merger of the hospital with New Haven Hospital, and this topic is reflected in correspondence with Orville Pelty, Harry C. Knight, Isaac Ullman, and B. Austin Cheney. With Knight, Ullman, and Frederick W. Campbell, Welch also discusses a site and plans for a new New Haven city hall. The files also contain minutes of meetings of the City Hall Building Commission. Other discussions of New Haven matters are contained in Welch's correspondence with Norris Osborn, editor of the New Haven Journal Courier. The files for the Military Training Corps Association relate to Welch's chairmanship of the association's Civilian Examining Committee.
Other files in Series I relate to Welch's insurance business and to his own and his friends' business investments. Folder 46 includes correspondence and royalty statements from the publisher of Yale: Her Campus, Class Room, Athletics.
Topics covered by material in Series II include Welch's participation in the Association Against the Prohibition Amendment, the Sentinels of the Republic, and civilian activities during World War I. For both the Association Against the Prohibition Amendment and the Sentinels of the Republic there are speeches, correspondence, and association literature. The files for the Sentinels of the Republic, an organization opposed to perceived encroachment of the federal government upon the rights of states and individual citizens, include several issues of the Woman Patriot. The World War I files also include material which Welch collected as background for speeches on behalf of the Connecticut State Council of Defense. Folders 202-204 contain copies of the Four Minute Men News, which was issued by the federal government's Committee on Public Information. The correspondence in folders 207-208 includes Welch's reports to various persons in the Military Intelligence Section of the Army War College on activities of alleged German sympathizers at Yale and in the New Haven area.
Biographical / Historical
Born July 9, 1867, in Hartford, Conn.
Died March 29, 1940, in New Haven, Conn.
Father, Henry Kirke White Welch (B.A. 1842). Mother, Susan Leavitt (Goodwin) Welch. Yale relatives include: Rev. Daniel Welch (B.A. 1749) (great-great-grandfather); Rev. Moses C. Welch (B.A. 1772) (great-grandfather); Sheldon C. Leavitt (B.A. 1802), George Goodwin (BA. 1806), Richard E. Goodwin (B.A. 1807), and Jonathan A. Welch (B.A.1813) (great-uncles); Edward Goodwin (B.A.1823) and Archibald Welch (M.D. Hon. 1836) (grandfathers); Rev. Moses C. Welch (B.A. 1850) and Sheldon Goodwin (B.A. 1858) (uncles); Arthur S. Goodwin, ex-'oo (cousin); and Franklin D. W. Glazier, '04, W. Stuart Glazier, '06, and Philip A. Glazier, ex-'07 S. (nephews).
Hartford Public High School. Oration appointment Junior year; dissertation appointment and Commencement speaker Senior year; second declamation prize Sophomore year; first Junior exhibition prize; editor Yale Literary Magazine Senior' year; assistant superintendent United Church Mission School three years; member Junior Promenade Committee, Committee to Preserve the Fence, Yale Assembly, Porter Literary Society, Hé Boulé, Psi Upsilon, Scroll and Key, and Chi Delta Theta.
On staff New Haven Register 1889-1890 and associate editor 1893-1895; City editor Hartford Courant 1890-1893; founder and first graduate editor Yale Alumni Weekly 1895-1896; established the magazine as permanent graduate publication and published and edited it until September, 1906, under supervision of an advisory board of graduates; New Haven representative Phoenix Mutual Life Insurance Company since 1909; president and treasurer Lewis S. Welch, Inc., general insurance, New Haven, since 1928; vice-president Life Underwriters' Association of New Haven 1927-1928 and president 1928-1929; director Brick Row Print and Book Shop 1922-1925 and Grace Hospital 1927-1929; member Committee on Revision of the City Charter, New Haven Chamber of Commerce (chairman town and city improvement committee 1909-1915,a vice-president 1921-1925, director 1923-1926), and Municipal Building Commission; chairman executive committee New Haven Thrift Week Committee 1924; chairman New Haven Branch, Military Training Camps Association; member Troop A, Connecticut State Guard, and civilian aide to Adjutant General of the United States during World War; treasurer New Haven branch Veterans Association of the Second Military District, 1921; vice-president Yale Alumni Association of New Haven 1921-1922, representative on Alumni Board 1923-1926 (member executive committee); member executive committee Yale-in-China 1903-1908, and on the council 1908-1914; secretary Kingsley Trust Association 1898-1908; chairman Class committee and member reunion committees since 1899; co-author: Yale, Her Campus, Class-Rooms, and Athletics (1899); author of a number of poems and pamphlets and contributed to Atlantic Monthly; honorary member Elihu Club; member national executive committee Sentinels of the Republic, New Haven chapter National Aeronautic Association, Elizabethan Club, and United Church (Congregational), New Haven (deacon 1918-1921).
Married December 8, 1897, in South Glastonbury, Conn., Mary Stuart, daughter of William Stuart and Mary Edwards (Goodwin) Williams, granddaughter of Solomon Williams ( ex-1803) and George Goodwin (B.A. 1806), great-granddaughter of Thomas Williams (B.A. 1748), and sister of George G. Williams, '80 S. Children: Emily Williams (B.A. Vassar 1921; Yale Graduate School and Yale School of Music 1922-1923), the wife of James Greil (Cornell ex-'29); Frances Goodwin (Columbia Univ. 1935-1939); and Elizabeth Edwards (B.A. Smith Coll 1927; M.A. Columbia 1932).
Death due to cerebral hemorrhage. Buried in Cedar Hill Cemetery, Hartford Survived by wife (died August 17, 1940), daughters, a grand-daughter, Mary Stuart Greil, a' sister, Mrs. Bernard T. Williams, and a brother, Henry Kirke White Welch, both of Hartford. Another Archibald A. Welch, '82, died in 1935.
Yale University Obituary Record, 1939-1940, pp. 43-44.
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open for research.
Yale Alumni Weekly; Insurance agents; Mines and mineral resources -- Arizona; Prohibition; World War, 1914-1918 -- United States; New Haven (Conn.); Businessmen; Bushnell, Winthrop; Chittenden, George B., 1849-1939; Delano, William W.; Goodwin, Burnett; Hotchkiss, Stuart H.; Ladd, Story B.; Norris, Osborn; Pinchot, Gifford, 1865-1946; Taylor, Z. Emery; Welch, Archibald Ashley, 1859-1935; Welch, Henry Kirke White; Welch, Lewis Sheldon, 1867-1940; Association Against the Prohibition Amendment; Grace Hospital (New Haven, Conn.); Saddle Mountain Mining Co; Yale College (1887- ). Class of 1889; Yale University -- Alumni and alumnae
- Correspondence, 1895-1933; Series I; 8 linear feet (20 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  This series is arranged in alphabetical order by correspondent or topic.
  - A, 1903-1904 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - B, 1896-1904 (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
  - C, 1897-1904 (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
  - D, 1898-1904 (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
  - E, 1902-1904 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - F, 1898-1904 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - G, 1896-1904 (Box 1, Folder 10-11)
  - Goodwin, Burnett, 1915-1918 (Box 1, Folder 12-20)
    General
    See also: box 9, folder 101 See also: box 10, folder 104-110
  - Grace Hospital, 1926-1930 (Box 2, Folder 21-30)
  - H, 1898-1904 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Hurst, George S., 1922-1930 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - J - L, 1896-1904 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Larned, Daniel Read, estate, 1915-1916 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - M - N, 1898-1904 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Marlin Arms Corporation, 1915-1917 (Box 3, Folder 36-37)
  - Military Training Camps Association, 1918 (Box 3, Folder 38-39a)
  - New Haven City Hall, 1920-1930 (Box 3, Folder 39b-43)
  - O - P, 1902-1904 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Osborn, Norris, 1925-1931 (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Page and Company, 1897-1904 (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - Phoenix Mutual Life Insurance Company, 1915-1918 (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - R, 1896-1903 (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - S, 1902-1920 (Box 4, Folder 49-51)
  - Saddle Mountain Mining Company
    - A, 1905 (Box 4, Folder 52)
    - B, 1903-1906 (Box 4, Folder 53-54)
    - Bookkeeper applications, 1904 (Box 4, Folder 55)
    - Bunce, W. H., 1903-1904 (Box 4, Folder 56)
    - Bushnell, Winthrop G., 1905-1913 (Box 5, Folder 57)
    - C, 1903-1905 (Box 5, Folder 58-61)
    - Chittenden, George B., 1901-1907 (Box 5, Folder 62-67)
      See also: box 5, folder 58-61 See also: box 8, folder 91
    - Chittenden, Samuel, 1905-1907 (Box 5, Folder 68-69)
      See also: box 5, folder 58-61
    - Copp, Alfred, 1905-1906 (Box 6, Folder 70)
    - D, 1902-1905 (Box 6, Folder 71-72)
    - Delano, W. W., 1906-1907 (Box 6, Folder 73a-75)
      See also: box 6, Folders 71-72
    - E, 1905 (Box 6, Folder 76)
    - Emery, Taylor Z., 1901-1903 (Box 6, Folder 77-78)
      See also: box 6, Folder 76
    - Emery, Taylor Z., 1904-1906 (Box 7, Folder 79-86)
    - Emery, Taylor Z., 1906-1907 (Box 8, Folder 87-88)
    - Executive committee, 1905-1906 (Box 8, Folder 89)
    - F, 1903-1905 (Box 8, Folder 90)
    - Financial records: reports from G. Chittenden, 1905-1906 (Box 8, Folder 91)
    - Financial records: general, 1904-1908 (Box 8, Folder 92-95)
    - Financial records: general, 1905-1906 (Box 9, Folder 96)
    - Financial records: bankruptcy clippings, 1906 (Box 9, Folder 97)
    - Francis, Charles, 1904-1907 (Box 9, Folder 98-100)
    - G, 1903-1905 (Box 9, Folder 101-102)
    - Garrison, E. E., 1906-1907 (Box 9, Folder 103)
    - Goodwin, Burnett, 1905-1912 (Box 10, Folder 104-110)
      See also: box 9, Folder 101
    - H, 1903-1905 (Box 11, Folder 111)
    - Hotchkiss, Stuart H., 1904-1907 (Box 11, Folder 112-115)
    - J - L, 1901-1904 (Box 11, Folder 116)
    - Ladd, Story B., 1901-1904 (Box 11, Folder 117-118)
    - Ladd, Story B., 1905-1907 (Box 12, Folder 119-122)
    - Lewis, Robert E., 1909 (Box 12, Folder 123)
    - M, 1893-1905 (Box 12, Folder 124)
    - Morehouse, S., 1905-1907 (Box 12, Folder 125)
    - N - Q, 1904-1906 (Box 12, Folder 126)
    - R, 1904-1905 (Box 12, Folder 127)
    - S, 1903-1906 (Box 12, Folder 128)
    - Scranton, Mary E., 1905-1907 (Box 13, Folder 129)
    - Squier, Frank, 1905-1907 (Box 13, Folder 130)
    - T, 1903-1905 (Box 13, Folder 131)
    - Taylor, Frank S., 1905-1906 (Box 13, Folder 132)
    - U - W, 1903-1907 (Box 13, Folder 133)
    - W - Z, 1904-1905 (Box 13, Folder 134)
    - Welch, A. A.: incoming letters, 1907-1908 (Box 13, Folder 135)
    - Miscellaneous, 1901-1905 (Box 13, Folder 136-139)
    - Miscellaneous: statements, 1903-1905 (Box 14, Folder 140-143)
    - Miscellaneous: letters, 1906-1909 (Box 14, Folder 144-147)
    - Miscellaneous, 1906-1914 (Box 15, Folder 148-151)
  - T - U, 1897-1904 (Box 15, Folder 152)
  - Taft, William H., 1913-1925 (Box 15, Folder 153)
  - Terra Marine, 1912-1917 (Box 15, Folder 154-156)
  - Thompson, Everad J., 1922-1924 (Box 15, Folder 157)
  - Tilson, John Q., 1923-1930 (Box 15, Folder 158)
  - U - W, 1893-1904 (Box 15, Folder 159-160)
  - Y, 1902-1903 (Box 15, Folder 161)
  - Yale University
    - General, 1897-1928 (Box 16, Folder 162a)
    - Alumni Weekly, 1902-1906 (Box 16, Folder 162b-163)
    - Alumni Weekly: Paterson affair, 1901 (Box 16, Folder 164)
    - Bull, William T., Fund, 1924-1933 (Box 16, Folder 165-166)
    - Class of 1887: general, 1901-1915 (Box 16, Folder 167)
    - Class of 1889
      - Poem, undated (Box 16, Folder 168)
      - Obituaries, 1924-1929 (Box 17, Folder 169-170)
      - Reunions, 1904-1929 (Box 17, Folder 171-177)
      - Reunions, 1929-1934 (Box 18, Folder 178-181)
      - Buel, Hillhouse, 1913-1917 (Box 18, Folder 182)
        See also: box 1, Folder 3
      - Correspondence, 1926-1928 (Box 18, Folder 183)
    - Cruiser fund, undated (Box 18, Folder 184)
    - Foreign Ministry Society, 1907 (Box 18, Folder 185)
  - Letterpress copybooks
    - 1903 August 24 - 1905 March 2 (Box 19, Folder 186-188)
    - 1905 March 2 - 1905 December 21 (Box 20, Folder 189-190)
- Subject Files, 1870-1934; Series II; 1 linear feet (3 boxes)
  This series is arranged by topic or type of material.
  - Photographs: family, 1895, undated (Box 21, Folder 191)
  - Prohibition: Association Against the Prohibition Amendment, 1925-1933 (Box 21, Folder 192-194)
  - Yale University Press, 1929-1934, undated (Box 21, Folder 195-196)
  - Scrapbook, 1910-1924 (Box 21, Folder 197)
  - Sentinels of the Republic: general, 1922-1925 (Box 22, Folder 198-199)
  - The Woman Patriot, 1921-1927 (Box 22, Folder 200)
  - World War I
    - General, 1914-1919 (Box 22, Folder 201-204)
    - Certificate, 1918 (Box 22, Folder 205)
    - Clippings and scrapbook, 1917-1918, undated (Box 22, Folder 206)
    - Correspondence: A - Z, 1917-1918 (Box 22, Folder 207-208)
    - Speech material, undated (Box 22, Folder 209-210)
  - Miscellanea, 1870-1927 (Box 23, Folder 211-218)